[Music]
hello good evening good day everybody
welcome to the ask a budget show i hope
you are doing very well
just like me
so uh let us see who all is there with
us i can see tukesh
akshay invincible amit
twilight informative
and
everyone else
ah great to see you all great to see you
all so as always i have picked a bunch
of questions and let us get right into
those questions
okay fifth question number one which is
by mega razz
india being gifted a seat in the
security council is the most ridiculous
myth
the security council was made up of the
vectors of ww2 and india was nowhere in
the scene of demanding little let alone
being gifted a seat at the table
if they could just give away a supreme
court's sea seat security council seat
why can't they gift it to india now when
we are strong country
and so on and so on and so so on and mr
nehru was very smart and he saw the
bluff that he was just dangling like a
carrot
and so on and so forth so
so there's not a question it's it's a
claim in this gentleman or person is
saying that i am wrong that
uh the offer i i have said that there
was an offer to the multiple offers to
india of a seat in the u.n security
council and this person is saying it's a
complete myth and i'm i'm completely
mistaken and mr nehru was a great
visionary and smart and all that
all right fine okay if you say so so
what's the evidence that i have
is there any evidence well let's let's
look at the evidence is there any
evidence
you don't believe me it's fine i get it
i get it you don't believe me but what
about this fine gentleman here
uh
this is an article from the hindu
january 10
2004 it says nehru declined offer of
permanent u.n seat
okay
and
read who says this
jawaharlal nehru declined the united
states offer to india to take the
permanent seat on the u.n united nations
security council around 1953 and
suggested that it be given to china
according to the then united nations
under secretary general
shri shashi tharurji
and that's what mr tharu has written in
his latest book of that time
nehru the invention of india
yeah
so if you don't believe me do you
believe the great
shri the
thiruji or not
do you do you not
and and let's let's examine this case
further
yeah
so there is uh this publication very uh
very prominent and famous publication
called the wilson center
yes the wilson center
uh
and this is an article from a few years
ago not at the coast of china
india and the u.n security council 1950
right so it's about
new evidence regarding us proposals to
nehru for joining the united nations
security council
uh and so on
uh
so there was an offer there was an offer
in
so mr tharur has
has uh revealed
like i showed that there was an offer by
the us by the united united states to mr
nero in 1953. now there is there was an
offer in 1955 also which was a soviet
offer
a soviet offer
and someone called nurani wrote a
defense of nero's decision and he tried
to say that this was just a feeler to
test india and so on but there was an
offer in 1955 all right by the by the
soviet union the ussr
uh
so mr nero said that the status of the
people's republic of china in the u.n
should take priority
before any consideration be given to the
necessary division of the u.n charter
for the admittance for of any new
permanent members so he said that even
you even though you're offering it to
india
the priority should be first given to
china
then there was also an offer in 1950
from the united united states
so 1950 u.s 1953 us 1955 ussr
three offers
yes
and mr nero said that india because of
many factors is certainly entitled to a
permanent seat in the in the security
council but we are not going in at the
cost of china
yeah
uh india's ambassador in beijing
optimistically briefed
that they believed in the uk and egypt
would support the prc's assumption
of china's security council seat giving
it majority support so they were
lobbying to ensure that china gets this
thing yeah
that's that's the kind of thing nehru's
determined rejection of the u.s plan to
place india in china's seat the u.n
security council reflected the
particular reverence and centrality
placed on the u.n by what one might call
a nehemian foreign policy
that nehru made so adamantly clear
that india did not want to replace china
in the u.n security council and
furthermore that the
issue of china's representation and the
u.n must take a priority
over any possible consideration of india
gaining a permanent seat in the body
underlies the centrality of china to
narrow foreign policy
okay and that's what it was so this
nehru's response to the us offer
underlined indian agency in its
difficult relations with the us so mr
nehru made things very difficult for
india by doing all these things the
united states wanted to offer that
permanent seat
in the u.n security council to india and
mr nero repeatedly rebuffed this offer
and he said that priority should be
first given to china only then should we
talk about india
whom was mr nehru serving
was he supposed to serve the people of
india the country the the nation of
india or was this supposed to serve the
people of china
yeah
who who was it supposed to serve that's
the question
so he repeatedly he repeatedly rejected
these offers not just from the united
united states but also from
the ussr and and here's something
interesting and then we know that then
there's also this offer that the us made
during president kennedy's time of
offering
nuclear weapons technology to india
and mr nero rejected that as well this
is before 1962 when india and china went
to war when china invaded india
had india acquired nuclear weapons
technology at that time china would have
not dared to invade india in 1962. so mr
nero ensured that this doesn't happen
now there's one more interesting piece
of evidence
this is after 1962. this is a news
clipping from 1963 please take a look at
this a news clipping from 1963
india still supports bid of china for
united nations seat
the sister of prime minister nehru said
on friday that india is ready to support
china's ambition to the united nations
even though her country fears a new
attack by chinese troops it's a matter
of principle it has nothing to do with
relations between any country and the
government of china vijaya lakshmi
pandith
the sister of mr neroji said at a news
conference in new york
yeah
i don't see how there can be a world
organization from which one fifth of the
world's pop people is excluded
so once again even after the chinese war
on india
mr nero and his sister were
pushing for china's inclusion in the
united nations security council at the
cost of india at the expense of india
so this is the kind of foreign policy
india had so these claims that mr nehru
was uh
smart enough to see something or
whatever and
this offer is a myth come on
who are you you're what world are you
living in whoever this gentleman or
person is
this is an established fact
multiple people very hierarchical people
have written about this mr tharu was
written about this former president mr
pranam mukherjee also wrote about this
in his book please go and read his book
and also about the the nepal affair i
mean everything will come out once we
start talking about these things
all right
so that's where we are we
we cannot deny the fact that mr nehru
was a magnificent
multi multi talented great great human
being shireen erugi
but uh facts are facts and facts don't
care about anyone's feelings so there we
are
all right
okay
let's move on
okay this is by namaneeth
how prepared are we to tackle any sort
of disturbance both internally and
externally regarding the g20 summit 2023
which is to be held in jammu and kashmir
what will be our neighbors plans
is this is this a major step towards
reclaiming what we have lost how will
this event change the outlook of people
on jnk and indeed india at the global
level uh
yes the next g20 summit the one in 2023
next year is going to be to be held in
jumbo and kashmir
so all these uh heads of state etc
whoever will participate will come to
india and they will come to jammu and
kashmir wherever this is being held and
the conference the meet will be the
summit will be organized and held over
there
so this
essentially
serves
as
a recognition by the whole world that
jnk is a part of india
right because there are certain uh
forces in the world that are trying to
to uh portray j and k as disputed
territory
we know which which forces these are
right so the g20 includes
the major industrialized and developing
nations of the world and they will all
participate in the summit in jnk which
essentially is a recognition of the fact
that jnk is part of india and will
always be and has always been part of
india right
so the question is
how prepared are we to to tackle any
disturbances we will be extraordinarily
well prepared
this is one of one of the most important
events that can happen the g20 summit
and we will take all possible measures
to ensure that it goes off smoothly
there will be certain forces certain
powers who will want to
make india look bad
and they have done things in the past
when president trump visited india in
delhi you know what happened in delhi at
the time and i wonder who was behind
that
these are forces that uh i mean
these events are often
orchestrated from outside india
right
so uh the same forces would want to do
something but this time i'm sure we will
be even better prepared and nothing is
going to be allowed to happen
now what about our neighbors plans
our neighbor always has bad plans they
always want to
throw a spanner in the works that's what
they want to do but it's very simple how
to deal with them all we all india will
have to do i'm sure it will be done
is inform
our neighbor
that no if if anything at all goes wrong
no matter who has done it we're gonna
blame you and you're gonna have to face
consequences you can't you can't even
imagine
that's all we have to tell the isi
and the generals
if something goes wrong it doesn't
matter who did it we're gonna put the
blame on you and you're gonna face the
consequences the kind of consequences
you cannot imagine
that's all we have to tell them
we are certainly in a position to send
pakistan back to the stone age if we
want to
so they also know it
so that's it that's all we have to do
and yeah so that's where we are is this
a major step towards reclaiming what we
have lost it's it's it's a process
we will eventually reclaim everything we
have lost and
and more
the time will come
uh so this is this is one step in that
process it's not a major or minor step
it's it's a step
in the process
right next
samarth says considering brics expansion
should india invite vietnam in the
philippines to prevent it from becoming
becoming china centric
what should be india's approach
according to you
so i don't think the brics has a formal
charter and a procedure for admitting
new members it's it's kind of an
informal kind of arrangement
uh initially it was just a brick bric
brazil russia india china four nations
uh until i think it was formed in 2006
or thereabouts
and a few years later south africa was
admitted so it went from a brick to
brics brics
now one hears that argentina and iran
have
requested admittance to this group
so it could
so i don't know what it will be called
then
b-r-i-i-c-s-a or something i don't know
what will be called uh so
this i think this offer this request has
been made to china possibly i'm not sure
who they've made to
uh
so there needs to be a proper consensus
about among the five countries as to
whom should be admitted who should not
be admitted and so on there should there
has to be a proper uh
uh
procedure
for uh process processing such uh such
requests and applications for admittance
to the brics group grouping
uh
i would not consider argentina to be
very
strongly pro-china iran of course
is now beholden to china after the big
deal that they have concluded
the chinese are going to invest
i don't know 40 billion or so dollars
40 billion 40 trillion i'm not sure yeah
it's not trillion it's billion maybe 40
50 billion dollars worth of money into
iran in various forms
so iran is now beholden to china if iran
enters brics the the grouping will
become more pro-china more china-centric
uh
so in that so
i am not sure that iran and argentina
will be admitted into the grouping
without taking the express consent and
permission from india
i suppose that the founding members
would have a veto as to who can be i
mean who can be admitted or not so i
this is something that's going to be
taken forward and i think all of these
things need to be formalized
the steps and procedures and all that
and there should be a proper charter
of the grouping what are the objectives
and what is the
how things should be taken forward and
all that
so eventually these things will happen i
think it's time for this grouping to
become more mature
and
yeah so once that is done then
these applications and requests can be
processed as per procedure
and things can be taken forward it is
important that this grouping does not
become too china centric china obviously
is the
largest
economy and most powerful nation
in the brics grouping uh from the
economic perspective china is number one
india is number two from the military
perspective china is number
two and russia is number one number one
perhaps something like that
uh so yeah we need balance in bricks and
this needs to be taken care of at the
appropriate levels
uh
so yeah that's where we are as of now
nothing uh
knows uh no decision has been made
about whether arjun theta and iran are
to be admitted or not but the offer has
come
come through and let's see what
how this is processed
okay your favor says india get
its first unmanned aircraft sdrdo tested
it successfully what are your thoughts
on this and what happens in drdo that
they have become so active so much
researching see drdo
is always active and and
implementing certain projects some of
these projects are classified that we
and we may not know about them this
particular project that you are
mentioning uh it has come out in the
open it is in the news it's called drdo
ghatak i think
so what does it look like what does this
aircraft look like let me show you
one second
it's a flying wing
aircraft it was called aura earlier now
it's called godpak
let me share the screen and show you
what the
aircraft looks like
so this is still
uh in the early days all right this is a
flying wing kind of thing it's a stealth
aircraft autonomous i'm not sure if it's
autonomous but it's uh
unmanned
so there are no pilots on this thing
it's an unmanned vehicle
uh this obviously is not an indian
vehicle but yeah all right it looks
something like this
and the first uh
test has occurred
it's of a scaled down model not a
full-scale model but yeah it
demonstrates the
that the technology works so now the
next step is that you make a full scale
model and you fly that
so this is uh how it is supposed to look
roughly
it's a draw you could call it a drone or
whatever it's a stealth combat drone
the gothic or swift or aura or whatever
the name is eventually they will name it
something else i suppose doesn't matter
so that's what's happened this is an
excellent step it's a very important
step this technology is something that
nobody will ever share with india nobody
will transfer this technology this is
cutting edge technology only uh three
countries i believe have this three or
four countries the u.s has it the
russians have it they have the authentic
aircraft
the chinese uh possibly may have
something like this i'm sure they do
and now we in india have this so this is
still
in development it's not uh come into
production
they they have to the drdo has tested a
scaled down version
of this aircraft but it works so it's
been proven the technology has been
demonstrated it's been proven now they
have to take it to the next step
create a full-scale version
test it out a prototype test the
prototype see how it works improve upon
it make two three more prototypes and
eventually you come up with the final
version that goes into production and
even that will be over time improved
upon and maybe that can give rise to a
whole class of aircraft you know uh
a
[Music]
reconnaissance drone a bomber a fighter
and things like that so these would have
different configurations different
weight classes and different payloads
and all those things
so that will happen eventually over the
next decade or so this is a very
important step an excellent step i am
very pleased to hear this
yeah
so uh good job drdo good job good job
government that you have
taken this forward
and
it needs to it needs to carry on
so they have drdo is active
uh
it's a good organization
the the thing is that it's it's well
i've spoken about this before like drdo
versus darpa both organizations were
started where
were founded in 1958 i believe and darpa
has gone so far ahead darpa darpa of the
us they have gone so far ahead and
they've come up with all kinds of
incredible technology dido is kind of
lagged behind india dude drdo has done
well
but
it hasn't reached the heights that darpa
has reached and there are very simple
reasons for that darpa and drdo have
very roughly similar budgets
similar budgets
but darpa has 150 employees drdo has 25
000 employees roughly
out of which 20 000 are non-scientists
so that's where all the money is being
misused it's been it's been used for
non-scientific purposes you cut out all
of the non-scientists all the
non-research stuff you keep on the
scientists and then you will see the
progress exponentiate kind of you know
so anyhow
this is excellent uh progress and uh one
must upload drdu and
please take it forward so good job very
pleased to see this
rohan vedata says how many
how many churches or mosques were built
by his royal highness
chatrapati shivaji maharaj during his
reign the question is simple but i
didn't get any satisfying answer from
the internet please answer this question
so i am not sure what sort of answer
would satisfy you but uh to the best of
my knowledge
his royal highness shri shattrapa
maharaja
built zero churches and zero mosques
during his reign
to the best of my knowledge
right
so
that's the answer i'm not sure if it
will satisfy you or not but that's the
answer uh that's to the best of my
knowledge if anybody has better
knowledge please share and please
correct me
but to the best of my knowledge
he did not build any church build any
churches or mosques right that's that's
the answer
right veera pratap says
i want to know your opinion
on the excavation conducted on the gulf
of kambay in the mid 2000s they had
found a sit sunken city of about five
square kilometers the interesting part
is that this is different from dwarka
yes
some of the artifacts they're predated
32 000 years which i find crazy
these artifacts were sent to different
countries for carbon dating can you
please tell us
your opinion
as a city
32 000 years years old seems to be quite
an impossible thing so from what i have
seen
uh this uh so
where is the gulf of cambe it's not
camby by the way it's khambhat
i don't know why we keep using these
foreign names for indian places so let's
take a look at the map and let's see
where it is the gulf of khambhat
it is in the sea of savarashtra which is
incorrectly called the arabian sea
right
similarly the bay of bengal is actually
kalinga mahasagar or kalinga sagar
anyhow the bay of khambhat is right here
it is the neck of gujarat if gujarat is
a face is if it's the face of india in a
way in a sense then this here is the bay
of khambat the gulf of hambada whatever
you want to call it this is the place
right and this is a very ancient region
and over here
over the past 20 years they have done a
few marine expeditions
in this region
and they have found evidence of human
inhabitations human settlements
underwater
right over here
uh including a fully formed city
which is apparently older
than
so this this date that you you're
mentioning here 32 000 years that's
something i have not seen anywhere
uh
they found
lots of artifacts
under the ocean
they found an entire city they don't
quite know what is the extent of the
city but it's a fully formed
well-developed city
and one of the pieces of
one of the artifacts they found was
carbon dated to about 9500 years before
today
so if that is the age of the city then
we have a full fully fledged fully
formed well developed city that is nine
and a half thousand years old that is
incredible because the oldest uh
saraswati hindu archaeological site that
we have which is bhirana in haryana is
nine and a half thousand years old and
that's very old
right
so that is tentatively held to be the
beginning of the saraswati sindhu phase
of india's civilization
now if this fully developed city
is nine and a half thousand years old
it's it's underwater that's that's
incredible that tells you that indian
civilization was highly developed ten
000 years before today
and now some people are are claiming
that you know
this date may be wrong because this
piece of wood may have come from
somewhere else
but think about it this way
this city
has been found
under the ocean
why is it found under the ocean
to understand why it's under the ocean
we have to understand when was the last
ice age
the last glacial period
of our planet
uh lasted from about a hundred and ten
thousand years before today 1.1 lakh
years before today to about 11 000 years
before today
so the last ice age ended about 11 700
years before today at the end of the
younger dryas period
and the last glacial maximum was about
20 000 years before before today
so when the last ice age was still in
force
yes
at that time uh let's see what the
geography of india looked like
so at that time the indian subcontinent
and its geography looked something like
this
as you can see there is a much more land
mass that was accessible
because it was a it was an ice age and
lots of water was actually frozen across
the oceans
and that's why the sea levels were much
lower than what they are today
and that's why india looked like this at
the time the indian subcontinent looked
like this
sri lanka was very much connected to
india the entirety of gujarat extended
far far
more westwards than what it does today
and so on this is what it looks like so
at that time it would have been possible
to have a city where today you have the
gulf of khambhat
right
and this is the last ice age which ended
about 11 700 years before today call it
consider it to be roughly twelve
thousand years before today
so if you have a city that's currently
under the ocean that city would have
been built at least twelve thousand
years before today
so the carbon dating nonsense is not
even an issue
if the piece of wood is 9500 years old
then it is younger
than the city
because the city has to be at least 12
000 years old for it to be under water
today
so that's where we are
so uh i don't know what the exact date
is the city is clearly minimum 12 000
years old a fully fledged fully
developed city
well planned city
larger than harappa and mohamed
and as well planned and as well
developed with with full architecture
and and swimming pool kind of thing and
whatnot
you know
so that's the kind of uh
architecture and technological
advancements we had in india 12 000
years before today at least
if not older so that essentially pushes
back
the timeline of indian civilization to
at least 12 000 years before today like
until i mean one
says people generally say that india is
10 000 years old at least right because
virana the oldest saraswati hindu
archaeological site is nine and a half
thousand years old
but this city in the gulf of hamburg is
at least 12 000 years old
and it's a fully developed city
so if it took about three four thousand
years for the technological development
to reach that stage then indian
civilization is at least 15 000 years
old and so on
so that is incredible so i don't know
about this dating that you are
mentioning of 32 000 years i have not
come across that anywhere
if you have then you can please let us
know in the comments and i'll take a
look at that but it's at least 12 000
years old that is guaranteed
that's incredible
that's older than the other side that
the people talk about go back they pay
and so on it's way older than that
incredible
isn't it
so
uh it it just keeps getting more and
more interesting right
history and archaeology
all right next question
rinegan says can you please talk about
the seven years devastation of manipur
and assam by the burmese from 1819 to
1826 many people don't talk about this
it's not even included even in our
history books even people in the
northeast don't know properly about this
tragedy it is said to be the equivalent
of the holocaust
while the burmese have always been
portrayed as a peace-loving society and
uh so on and so forth right okay the
seven years
devastation of manipur
that's what they call it from 1819 to
so this was a terrible terrible time
seven years of of complete devastation
of manipur at the hands of the burmese
empire or kingdom right so what is this
what happened there
so to understand what happened you have
to go back i always go back a couple of
centuries in time so let's go back just
a little bit
uh it all
begins
so to say
with the the manipuri king
so pam iba is uh considered to be uh
the most successful conqueror in the
past one thousand years in manipur right
uh he was the son of pitambar
charirongba
so parmaibal ruled from about 1690 to
about 1750
and he is the king who introduced
vaishnavism as the state official state
religion of manipur at the behest of uh
what was his name
some bengali preacher so what he did was
he introduced gaudiya vaishnavism being
the bengali form of vaishnavism as the
official state religion of manipur and
he
indulged in multiple military conquests
he was a very successful conqueror
pam
uh his his kingdom
spanned
from uh the iravati river the ira wadi
river in burma in the east to kachar and
tripura in the west and it also included
the so-called chittagong hill tracts
which are currently in bangladesh right
so he was one of the most successful
military conquerors of manipur in the
past thousand or so years he also
introduced vaishnavism as the official
state of gaudiya vaishnavism
uh
as the official state religion in in
manipur which kind of uh
which kind of in some sense transformed
the manipur society from a society of
warriors to society of of people who
kind of
uh looked at other things uh with uh
yeah that sort of thing you know
into a more peace-loving society it's
there's nothing wrong with being
peace-loving but it kind of
softened up manipura society this
specific form of vaishnavism gaudiya
vaishnavism
now what happened is that when uh
pamela died the succession went wrong he
had a good son a capable son whose name
was
whose name was shia masai
but
this shamasai was assassinated by his
own brother ajitsai
and there was this
squabble for succession and you know
there was a lot of political instability
eventually the assassinated son's
son
which means the grandson of pamela whose
name was ching tang komba
became the king of manipur he was a very
good king he ruled for about 50 years he
was known as the rajashi bhagat chandra
he introduced i mean manipure classical
dance and a great deal of culture and
all that
and then
after
after the deaths of
bhaga chandra you had a couple of kings
who came on
who ruled who were not that
good as rulers and so on
and then
manip the manipuri king kind of became a
vasal of the of the burmese
and then there was a new burmese king
who came to power he ordered the
manipuri king to attend the coronation
the manipuri king refused and in
retaliation the burmese king sent an
army
invaded manipur conquered manipur and
then there was seven years of
devastation in which at least five lakh
manipuris were murdered
half a million and another at least
another three lakh manipuri men women
children were taken as slaves
into burma and today their descendants
would still live today and lots of
manipuris had to escape from manipur and
go into
assam and bank even bengal and all
and that gave
gave rise to the bishnupriya manipuris
and all that so it was a terrible period
seven years of complete devastation the
burmese tried to eradicate the manipuri
people completely
because burma and manipur had been
had been at war from time to time in a
cyclic manner for centuries
and the bani and the burmese wanted to
completely eradicate manipur as a threat
forever
so they tried to uh essentially conduct
genocide in manipur
imagine manipur is a small place
do we even know where manipur is let's
take a look at the map
excuse let's take a look at the map and
see where manipur is
where's the map
here's the map
here is the map
so let's go here
so if you can see
this is the city of impal which is the
capital of manipur
and to the east you have burma
to the south you have a yangon rangoon
and so on mandalay a major city
and then you have the great irawati
river which i believe is this here it is
the ira
called it
so that's the region we're talking about
so the the burmese invaded manipur they
occupied manipur for seven years they
killed at least half a million manipuris
took another three hundred thousand plus
money puris as slaves
and devastated the place they would what
they would do is they would
put manipuri men women and children uh
in an enclosed house or something
shut them inside
and then burn chillies and suffocate
them by by burning them burning the
chillies and kill them that way so very
very brutal kind of occupation
which lasted for seven years eventually
what happened is that the king of
manipur
whoever was the king at the time
he uh
brought in the british
right so the british got involved in
this then there was the first
anglo-burmese war i think in 1824 or
something
and eventually the british got involved
because of this so manipur was freed
from the burmese the manipuri king had
to become kind of a vasal of the british
the british were already ruling other
parts of india at the time especially
bengal bengal is the first colonized
place in india and the effects are still
visible
so uh
so that's how the british got involved
and eventually in 1891 there was the
anglo manipuri war
which the manipur is lost and manipur
was totally destroyed from there onwards
so the uh manipuri royal lineage was
destroyed and a puppet king was put in
place
and manipur became a princely state and
today's so-called manipuri kings are
descendants of those puppets
that's how it is every single princely
state in india
was in some way
or some shape or form a collaborator
with the british so that is what
happened and that is in brief the story
of the seven years devastation of
manipur
uh which was a disastrous period which
changed manipur forever
so that's what it was
okay saurabh says who was amazu
mentioned in the bodhiana
sutra was he the founder of the persian
civilization
interesting question who was
right who is this person
let's take a look at who was amazon
so
once again let me let me share my screen
so this is an article i wrote in 2017
this is where it all began the rn
invasion thing
in this article which i wrote in 2017 i
had put together all the evidence from a
variety of different disciplines
archaeology and geology and linguistics
and genetics and whatnot
so let's take a look at this particular
uh
piece of evidence
so this is the bodhiana sutra which is a
late vedic text
so it recalls that
it's a sanskrit text obviously it's a
vedic text it says that amavasu migrated
westward
his people are the gandhari the parshu
and the aratha
okay that's what this
text says so this refers to a vedic king
called amavasu whose people are the
gandhari which is clearly the people of
gandhar afghanistan
then the parshu which is clearly the
persians or our
persian brethren ancestrend
and the arata so the aratha tentatively
identified as living in the vicinity of
mount ararat in
anatolia and armenia
so uh so that's what it is now
the traditional armenian name for mount
ararat is masis
it is named after the legendary armenian
king ammasiya
this name amasiya is linguistically
related to the name of our vasu of the
indian king recorded in the bodhiana
surat sutra right so that is who amma
vasu is that's what we know that is the
evidence that we have that's the
information that we have
so the question so so that is amavasu he
was a vedic king from the vedic period
late vedic period
and apparently he migrated westward with
his people and his people are identified
as three the separate to ethnic groups
of today the gandhari which is the
afghans of today the
portions of today and the aratha which
which seems to be the armenians or the
people around mount ararat
that's what it seems to be
so the real question is was he the
founder of the persian civilization it's
the text says that his people are the
persians as well the parshu
but um
i would not say that amma was the
founder of the persian civilization
because uh
the persian civilization was founded by
the parshwa clan
which was one of the clans that ended up
on the losing side in the battle of the
ten kings which happened possibly in a
pre rigvedic era
possibly
so uh that would certainly predate the
time
of the bodhian ashrae sutra
so somehow it seems that amma wasu was
really related to the gandhari people to
powerful people and the
arata people
which people
yeah there are other people
so
so we don't know in what way he was
related to them
but somehow he was so maybe that's
something that needs to be researched
further and but we need to try to
unravel in what way are the
his people i mean three different ethnic
groups of today across three different
geographical regions how are these three
ethnicities related to the same king so
that's something that me that is an
intriguing question it needs to be
investigated but i would not say that uh
amma was the founder of the persian
civilization maybe he was the founder of
the armenian
uh
ethnicity or whatever perhaps
so that's something that needs to be
investigated so that's what we know for
sure and that actually raises more
questions
all right
okay mohan kumar says i watched your
recent podcast with ranveer and the
questions
arose were
who exactly were the nazis
what made them kill so many jews and
gypsies who were the gypsies what were
concentrations concentration camps like
that's a whole lot of questions and one
let me try and simplify things and give
you a brief overview who were the nazis
the nazis were the national total party
of germany
so
germany lost world war one
uh they they fought this war
in an alliance with the austro-hungarian
empire the habsburg dynasty
and the ottoman empire right the entire
business of world war one started with
the assassination of archduke of frank
49 france franz ferdinand in sarajevo in
june i think 1914 was it june or july
june 1914 right
and uh
the austro-hungarian empire blamed
serbia for this thing and they declared
war on serbia after first consulting
germany germany said go ahead go go
fight them
and then germany after after serbia
after the austro-hungarians declared war
on serbia the germans got involved they
declared war on france they invaded
france
and the russians got involved because
they were on the side of
they were in an alliance so to say with
serbia
the moment the germans invaded
invaded belgium and then france the
british got involved so the whole of
europe suddenly went into into this big
conflict the ottomans sided with the
germans
the italians
remained neutral for some time and then
they fought against the
austro-hungarians in 892 battles on the
issanzo river
well not really 1892 maybe more than 10
battles
it was a complete stalemate and so on so
eventually the germans
lost the austro-hungarian empire was
dismantled thoroughly completely
the ottoman empire was dismantled
completely thoroughly
germany lost much of its uh not much of
its territory maybe 10 or 20 of its
territory poland was recreated germany
was humiliated in the treaty of
versailles they were made to sign this
treaty in which they had to explicitly
said they state that
the entire war was our fault
and they were made to pay enormous
reparations huge reparations
to the uh to the to the countries they
fought against
so this ended in 1999 there abouts the
1920s was a very bad period for germany
uh they were humiliated they were beaten
they were paying enormous reparations to
other countries their economy had
completely collapsed there was hyper
inflation then the 1929 stock market
crash of a wall street crash happened
which further affected the german
economy and so on so the german people
were humiliated
that pride was destroyed
and that gave rise to nationalism in
germany also in italy
because italy also felt that it gained
nothing out of its of all of its efforts
in world war one
so in italy you had the rise of fascism
beneath the mussolini
in germany there was this right of
nationalism under the national socialist
party called the nazis the nazi party
it's an abbreviation
and their leader was adolf hitler
who appealed to german pride he promised
that he would bring the german pride
back he would restore german pride
restore german glory and make germany
great again
that sort of thing right
so uh
so he came to power in the 1930s it was
the end of the weimar republic and very
quickly he became
the paramount ruler of germany the
dictator of germany the fuhrer
yeah
and he so that's what happened
now um
when things go wrong you need to find
someone to blame
right
so is so
the nazis
focused all their hatred
and and singled out
the uh the jews firstly
as the enemy of the nation as the
enemies of the nation
and there were these pogroms against the
jews there was kristallnacht
and a whole lot of stuff that happened
so the jews were demonized they were
portrayed as the enemy within
and again lots of other people were
demonized seventh-day adventists and the
homosexuals and people with the
disabilities and the romani people the
gypsies who were not white
so the germans what they did was they
stole an ethnicity
the aryan ethnicity they said that the
the german the white people are the
audience they stole the ethnicity of the
indo-iran iranian people if any ethnic
group can be called aryan today it is
the indians and the iranians and no one
else in the world
the the so-called aryan race is not a
white race it's a brown race it's the
brown people it's the indians and the
iranians who are aryans nobody else can
be called aryans but these germans the
nazis they stole that that the title
that that ethnic self-designation and
they said that the white people are the
audience and they said that the jews and
the romanis etc are unaryans or
non-aryans which is nonsense because
because romania should be the real
aryans right in in europe because they
are of indian origin anyhow they
demonized these people
and eventually what happened was
genocide they they ended up killing
about four million or so
jews and at least a million romanis
indian origin gypsies in in various
man in various ways in concentration
camps
uh
treblinka sobibor
auschwitz and so many other horrific
places which
yeah which still exists today i suppose
yeah very morbid places for tourism so
that's what happened
it was it was tragic
terrible
especially the treatment of
yeah jews and gypsies
so yeah that that in short is what
happened and
what would the concentration comes like
well the worst place you can imagine and
multiply that by a hundred
yeah it's where people went to die the
people were taken to die by typically by
by railroad
uh they used to pack these people into
into railway compartments
and send them by train to people to
places like auschwitz and sobibor etc
then the people the the jews would be
taken there and
the ones who had specialized
skills would be used for as a slave
labor
the others would be just uh
gassed to death terrible terrible
business
so yes that's what happened a very
horrific chapter of history and
well yeah
so that's your answer sir in brief
next question is by yash
is it true that many nazi scientists
were recruited by the us to work in nasa
and that they were pioneers of their
initial success and now whatever they
are achieving is primarily due to asian
intellect india south korea china etc
all right
so
nazi germany germany
uh
so germany was unified for the first
time in 1871
due to the efforts of uh the great
bismarck chancellor bismarck
ortofon bismarck right
until that time germany was a fragmented
uh disunited
collection of
of uh
kingdoms and things like that right
so bismarck united germany for the first
time in 1871
and then he instituted instituted a
series of reforms which completely
transformed this new nation into a
an industrial superpower it became the
engine that was driving europe
and germany uh ended up
becoming the pioneer in all kinds of new
technologies including missile
technology rocket technology
and so on
and
it is scientists like werner von braun
who were the pioneers of rocket
technology
so germany is the first nation that
produced cruise missiles and ballistic
missiles v1 was the cruise missile that
bombed london
lots of times and other places in europe
as well
and v2 was the
first ballistic missile
which was reasonably accurate and
so the germans were the pioneers of
cruise missile technology and rocket
technology and jet engine technology and
they also had a very
very very uh efficient and
innovative military industrial complex
there were pioneers in aviation as well
they had some of the best aircraft of
world war ii fighter aircraft other
aircraft the measure smith's the stukas
the hangels
and so on and so forth right
the british had a good aircraft the
spitfire
and the americans had a good aircraft
called the mustang but the germans
overall had the best
family of aircraft so the germans were
incredible
innovators
in military technology rocket technology
jet engine technology and all that when
world war ii ended
the americans
and the russians were in possession of
roughly half and half of germany the
russians had taken over berlin
they are the ones that took berlin and
that precipitated adolf hitler's
apparent alleged suicide yeah
although the body has never been found
uh apparently we don't know
so uh
at the end of world war ii
the soviets were in possession of the
eastern half roughly of germany and the
americans were in possession of the
western half roughly of germany the
americans gathered as many
german scientists as they could and they
were lucky to get hold of werner von
braun
if you want to see what mr font brown
looked like
let me show you what there is
let me
share my screen
so what the americans did is they
captured as many
german scientists
as they could
this is werner von braun
that's what he looked like
he was a german scientist
this is him during world war ii
he was obviously a member of the nazi
party
and
the americans captured him and a number
of other german scientists and the
americans were lucky enough to capture
the cream of the german scientists
and they were taken prisoner
and shipped off to the united states
along with captured rockets like the v2
rocket and all that so all of this
equipment and the scientists were taken
to america in what is called operation
paper clip
operation paperclip
the russians captured whoever else they
could find
and those
german scientists they were able to
capture were taken to russia
so the americans took
mr von braun
and a number of rockets missiles and all
that they took them to the us
here you have mr kennedy president
kennedy with 101 brown
and eventually
werner von braun became the head of nasa
and he is the person that essentially
developed
the saturn v rocket which took
the first human beings to the moon
that's what happened right
so
the american space program
was essentially built by
nazi scientists
nazis rocket scientists and engineers
and it's not just the saturn 5 rocket
that mr von braun developed he developed
the entire
range of rockets that came before that
it was all done with german technology
nasa did not develop its technology from
scratch it acquired technology from the
nazis and used that and dev and built
upon that
the americans have not developed their
own technology they used nazi technology
the soviets
also built their first rockets using
nazi technology like the r2 rocket and
so on and so forth which eventually
became a whole family of rockets
that they built so
even the russians even the soviets built
their space program on the back of
german
rocket technology
and during the period of cooperation
between the ussr and china mao china
the soviets transferred rocket
technology to the chinese
which was nazi rocket technology so the
chinese rocket program space program was
also built on the back of on a
foundation of nazi technology
and then they built a whole bunch of
rockets based on that technology
so the u.s
rocket program the u.s space program the
whole of nasa
the soviet space program
and the chinese space program were all
based on technology taken from the nazis
it's only the indians
that developed the rocket technology
entirely from scratch
and maybe the japanese as well
and maybe the french bus perhaps i'm not
sure what what is the history of the
french rocket program but that's what it
is
so all of these nations
they acquired rocket technology space
technology from the nazis and the
pioneer
is werner von braun
right he was the
he eventually he was a prisoner for the
longest period of time for many years he
was always under surveillance and slowly
over time he
he graduated so to say
to become the head of nasa
and eventually yeah so that's what it
was he still looks like a prisoner here
doesn't he even though he's the head of
nasa so that's how it was so that is the
story
uh and now whatever they're achieving
here they've got so many immigrants the
the americans
so much of nasa and much of the these
big companies they have lots of indian
indian engineers who work there and yeah
that's that's a known fact
so that's the story
ujjaan chakraborty says my question is
that india or u.s will send
will india or the u.s send army to
afghanistan to throw away the taliban
regime from there and build bring back
the old original democratic government
see the americans
withdrew from afghanistan the americans
were in power
well they were in
they occupied afghanistan for roughly 20
years
from 2001
until 2021 20 years
and they chose to leave the country and
they chose to hand over power to the
taliban
so why would they go back and
remove the taliban when they put they
installed the taliban in the first place
so there is no chance of america doing
any such thing
secondly india why should india get
involved in this matter
what does india stand to gain
how does it
further india's national interest
by sending our army there and fighting
taliban what do we gain from that
and isn't it risky to send our army
to a place where we don't have a direct
land route as of as of today
so it doesn't make any sense
strategically or from the national
interest perspective for india to get
involved and and try to overthrow the
taliban we can do it if you wish to but
why would we do it we have reasonably
good relations with taliban with the
taliban
and we have a common enemy with the
taliban so why would would we want to
fight them
for democracy
what democracy which democracy
are you one this illusion that uh
the government that was in power in
afghanistan for the past 20 years was a
democratic government
it was a puppet regime placed there by
the united states
when a foreign occupying power holds
elections those elections are not free
and fair
those are staged elections
when a foreign power comes and occupies
your country militarily
and then holds elections there do you
consider that to be free and fair
elections are free and fair only when
there is no foreign interference
so the government that was in power in
afghanistan for 20 or so years whether
it was under under mr ashraf ghani
or or mr karzai whoever it was these
were puppet regimes
there was no democracy there these were
deeply corrupt regimes incredible
amounts of u.s money flowed into
afghanistan for building roads and
infrastructure and schools and all that
where are those roads and infrastructure
in schools where where is all that
where are all those schools
where all those roads where is all the
infrastructure what happened to all the
money
that money was actually used
to buy politicians and keep them
appeased deeply corrupt regimes
okay
the taliban actually may may represent
the will of more of afghans than the
than those paper regimes
there was this pupol
pew survey or whatever which said that
uh the majority of the afghan population
wants sharia law and all that which is
what the taliban gives them now
obviously the pew polls cannot be taken
without a few grains of salt
but that's what it is
so i think the taliban actually
represents the will and the wishes of
more afghans than not
and certainly it represents afghanistan
more accurately than the
when then the puppet regimes of the
americans are installed there
and india and the taliban have a good
understanding
and we have a common
adversary
so there is no reason why would india
would get involved and try to overthrow
the taliban why would we do it
what do we ge
stand to gain from this
democracy what democracy
democracy is an illusion my friends
okay this is by vamsi
why france is another russia to india we
people hate the west now
uh what's your views on france and
what's the difference between west and
france why france is against world big
brother interest and why germany and
france are not happy with the us
interest okay okay okay okay
no one hates the west i don't hate the
west i've lived in the west with the
there is so much to learn from the west
i have absolutely nothing against the
people of the west but yes the west is a
force of of that has caused an enormous
amount of harm to the world
it has destroyed africa it has destroyed
asia
and so on so we will not go get into
that now what's the the question is why
is france another russia india well
france is not another russian india
but yes
okay the other question is what's the
difference between the west and france
there is no difference between the west
in france france is very much part of
the west
france too has been a major colonial
power france too has indulged in a great
deal of destruction especially in africa
so you can't absolve france of all of
that france and france
instituted slavery in the west indies
and so on so france has a very dark
history it still interferes greatly
in africa in the internal matters of
african countries
in north africa and so on
the sub-saharan region and
and so on and so forth
so france is very much part of the west
it is culturally and geographically part
of the west it is part of the european
union an integral part of the european
union which is essentially
a bunch of nations that is dominated by
the us
france is also part of nato which is
again
a bunch of vasal states of the us the eu
is a large bunch of american vassal
states
nato is a smaller group of nations that
are u.s basal states right
but
among all of these nations
france is the only nation
that has
a reasonably independent foreign policy
it decides it makes its own decisions
which are not
uh influenced by by american
interests
and that's why there is a great deal of
friction between france and the u.s from
time to time to time it keeps happening
and there are calls within france
for france leaving nato that france
should leave nato
and uh yeah that's the relationship that
is the fraught relationship france has
with the us it's the only nation in the
eu and nato that has an independent
foreign policy that is not completely
under the heel under the boot
of the u.s
and france has excellent relations with
india france was the only major western
power that did not condemn the 1998
indian nuclear tests
and france and india have what you could
call a strategic relationship today a
strategic and military relationship
excellent relations
uh
our interests converge in a great number
of matters
and there's a great deal of cooperation
on military friend on the military front
and other fronts as well on in diplomacy
and a great deal of convergence in
geopolitics as well
so yeah in that sense france could be
considered to be in some ways in in some
ways kind of like russia but not really
like russia
so that's that's the situation
germany and france are not happy with
the u.s interests well germany has
no choice germany is under permanent u.s
military occupation
uh
so germany has no option it is it is a
fully uh
colonized state state so to say
uh it doesn't have an independent
foreign policy or an independent
internal policy either
germany is the u.s colony it's you it's
a u.s fossil state not a colony of assad
state
france is not
so that's that's what the situation is
and obviously
at the ground level people will not be
happy about this people can see what's
happening especially when you're living
in the country
that there is no actual autonomy
your leaders are all subservient to the
american interest so people can see it
and that's why people are not happy with
that
but at least in france there is
independence of foreign policy and
internet policy and that's why there is
friction between the france and the us
the recent auk-us deal the french
had signed a deal with the australians
to supply a number of scorpion
submarines to australia the deal was
signed it was a done deal
and then the australians walked out of
it because the americans arm twisted
them into walking out of it
so that brought in a big great deal of
friction between france and the u.s and
australia and that's something that is a
pattern that keeps continuing so that is
the situation overall and india and
france have very good relations
aneesh says can japan germany and other
countries which are under u.s occupation
or influence ever rebel against it
do the governments or the people of
these countries even want to be free
from the hegemony what can be the
repercussions of such a collective
rebellion against the us
these countries are in no position
to rebel against the us
japan is under heavy us military
occupation
if there is a rebellion it will be
crushed in an instant
but the us is in full
control of japan
the japan japanese constitution was
written in 1945 or thereabouts by
americans
it's never been changed not a single
word has been changed
in the past 70 plus years
the u.s has
dozens of military bases
in japan
including major bases
i suppose there could be nuclear weapons
i'm not sure about that but yeah
so the japanese are com
completely under the under american
control and occupation there is no
chance of them
rebelling against that any i mean the
americans would have planned in 1945
itself how
to deal with a potential rebellion and
as they took more and more control of
the country
that became an impossibility the only
way this could end is if u.s influence
wayne and the u.s
declined so much they have to withdraw
from japan the way the romans had to
withdraw
from the british islands
a long time ago
yeah
so the japanese have no chance of
rebelling if they try they'll be crushed
immediately
and it won't be it won't even appear in
the media that's what will happen
uh germany again has no chance germany
is under
the entirety of western europe
is under u.s control essentially apart
from france
so uh
and the u.s has military has nuclear
weapons in in places like the
netherlands and belgium even in turkey
they have military bases everywhere
permanent bases in japan in germany in
italy
i suppose there could be bases in spain
also the americans have complete control
of the uk as well
and so on
so uh the only situation scenario in
which this hegemony
and occupation will end
is if the u.s declines like the roman
empire did
and when the roman empire declined they
had to withdraw
from the british islands and other
places and that's how these people these
places became free again
so that is one scenario in which
these people could be free
from
u.s hegemony now usa germany may not be
a bad thing for europe
europe has historically been
a place
of deep ethnic divides deep ethnic
hatreds and constant war the past 70
years of relative peace after world war
ii
have been because of pax americana
because the americans were the dominant
power in western europe and they were
counter balancing the ussr and after the
decline and dissolution of the ussr
it was nato that was expanding and it is
the american influence that kept the
region stable and kept war at bay except
for
things like the the
the breakup of the of yugoslavia which
the americans engineered and so on so
forth so when they want war they will do
it but overall there's been peace until
now in europe since 1945 because of the
american influence
so if the americans leave these
countries will again go to war they have
old scores to settle against each other
which won't be a nice thing
so that's where we are that's what the
history is and that's what could happen
okay a couple of questions one is by
weibo the u.s has offered to develop
amca jet engine together which they
denied previously currently drdo is in
talks with safran
what do you think the us will why what
do you think
u.s take 180 degrees turn do we go with
franz safra abhimanyu says i
recently read u.s offering india to
jointly manufacture jet engine for our
amca
amca is
the fifth generation jet fighter that
india is currently developing
so why making and manufacturing jet
engines is so difficult for india
especially when considered that india
already has cryogenic engines and
indigenously developed missile launcher
systems okay
let's deal with the second question
first why is it so hard to build to
manufacture jet engines because it's a
very difficult technology only a handful
of countries have mastered it
and that process has taken decades
decades seven or so decades the british
have the rolls-royce engines
the americans of the general electric
engines the french of the smith snikema
or saffron engines
the chinese uh the russians have their
own saturn and other engines turbo turbo
fan and all that all those engines
and the chinese are trying to develop
reasonably good engine the w whatever
series of engines they are not quite
successful thus far but they are making
significant strides in the right
direction
it takes a huge amount of
research and development and trial and
error and iterative progress to develop
a good jet engine it's a very long
difficult process
and the reason for that is that jet
engines are very complicated
machines
extremely high temperatures
which would melt most metals
and yet you need the turbo fan to to
withstand those temperatures
and not disintegrate
that's why many i mean for instance with
the fox bat
uh mig 25 was it the fox bat
which could travel it at mach 2 or
higher
at very high altitudes
if you took it to its maximum speed it
would fly but when it comes back and
lands you would have to replace the
engines because they would be ruined by
the time that's how it was
so jet engines are
they they
operate at very high temperatures at
very high stresses
and uh
that's why it's so difficult to build
them you need to come up with with
exotic materials composite composite
materials or you need to build those jet
jet engine turbine blades out of a
single crystal of metal which is
technology that most countries can't
even imagine having right
so that's why it is so difficult the
americans have been
developing their jet engines the general
electric engines for for decades
and so on so
the same goes for the uk and the
russians
and the french the chinese are still
trying to catch up they're still at
least a generation behind
the top nations
and
in india
we have uh
we we have drdo and it has a lab in
bangalore i believe which
which uh
does research with jet engines we have a
cavalry engine which is not quite right
for our fighter aircraft
the amount of thrust it produces is
approximately 70 or so kilonewtons
uh way for for the for a fighter plane
we would need at least 90 kilonewtons or
so
and for something like the amca
or the twin engine
deck based fighter etc you would need
very powerful jet engines
with a thrust of about 125 or so
kilonewtons or thereabouts
so that's the kind of output we know we
need and the cavalry engine hasn't been
able to achieve that output so
india has now decided that for the
amca
advanced medium combat aircraft the
fifth engine fighter we are building
the initial mach one model of the of
this plane will have general electric
american engines
so that in the mark two will have indian
engines
so then for that we need to develop an
indian engine and for that we need a
foreign cooperation maybe transfer of
technology whatever it doesn't matter
pay the money get the technology and
then take it forward
so india is considering
an offer from france safran
and also nowadays like like you say the
americans have have made an offer
of developing the technology
jointly
so i believe the technology they are
offering is a it will will give us a jet
engine that has uh
which which has an output of about 110
kilonewtons or something
but i think we need 125
ideally so let's see how it goes i would
say that india should go with the french
because the french are more trustworthy
the americans have don't have a very
good track record when it comes to
cooperation with india
so one has to be careful
you're investing good money and we don't
want to lose that and we need the
technology as soon as possible
so i i would prefer
i mean at the end of the day for the
government to make their make a choice
make a call they know better than us
they will know information that we don't
have but my gut feeling is that france
would be a better choice for india
so let's see
what happens
okay so the siddhant says
recently heard news that india will give
lca pages to egypt what will be the
reaction of israel on this
how will india manage weapon deal and
good friends like israel okay right so
israel is not a friend israel is a
nation with which we have very good
relations because we have shared
interests common interests
there are no friends or enemies in
geopolitics there are temporary
alliances and temporary adversaries and
things can change but
you have certain nations with which you
have long-term shared interests and
israel is is one of those nations along
with nations like france and russia etc
so the news is that india say india is
not giving anything to anyone
we are not giving anything we'll be
selling if if the deal happens we will
be selling something to them we're not
giving it it's not a gift
so there are two nations that are
interested as of today
in the lca pages one is malaysia the
malaysians i don't know how many uh jet
aircraft they need maybe 20 or so
roughly
if correct me if i'm wrong
so they need this aircraft and
they have i think the lcts may be the
front runner that they are considering
so most likely they will go with the lca
teachers
uh so
i think a malaysian
delegation is going to visit visit india
very soon
to see the production facilities and and
take a look at the how the aircraft is
and maybe test it out or whatever
so whatever
they will have to do they will do it
and
so the lcds is a front runner when it
comes to malaysia
the tejas has a very good advantage it's
a very light aircraft
it's a very capable aircraft and it's a
very cheap aircraft it
the cost per per unit is about 42
million dollars which is among the
cheapest in the world and it's a very
good aircraft so lots of countries are
interested so the malaysians could
likely acquire this plane from india
which is good
and india has also offered this to egypt
the egyptians need many more
i don't know maybe 80 or so so what
india has offered is that we have
offered egypt we have offered
to
to build a production plant in egypt
itself
so we will
create a whole production line in egypt
and the planes will be built there
and from there they can
the the they can be built for the
egyptian requirements maybe 70 80
whatever they need and then more can be
manufactured and sold to other countries
in the
middle east north africa region
and many countries would be interested
because it's a very capable and cheap
aircraft
many uh north african countries need
fighter aircraft for their requirements
and maybe some middle eastern countries
as well
and
the american planes etc are very
expensive so they may want to go with
the lcds so india is offering to build
an entire production plant in egypt and
india i believe is also offering a
variety of helicopters to egypt so we
have the uh
the
light combat helicopter which is a very
capable helicopter it's uh
it can fly at very high altitudes in in
seattle etc
it can also fly in extremely hot
environments like in the thar desert in
rajasthan so it's a brilliant very good
helicopter and we are offering that to
egypt along with the advanced light
helicopter and
some other
aerial platforms so that's what is
happening right now and let's see how
that goes forward
uh
what about israel well israel will not
be happy with this only if this deal
threatens israel's national interest
and that is not the case israel has had
a very good relationship with egypt for
the past several decades
uh
and of course we would uh not do
anything that would that would uh
be perceived as as
something negative by israel for sure
because we value the the relationship
that we have with israel
so whatever deal is reached it will not
be
so these aircraft or these weapons
systems will not be sold to any
countries
that have an adversarial relationship
with israel egypt is not one of these
nations egypt has a very reasonably good
relationship with israel and israel is
now
uh
so now we have diplomatic relations
opening up between israel and various
gulf countries as well
uh including the uae and maybe even the
saudi arabians
so things are changing in the middle
east after the
abraham accords that president trump
presided over and so on so things are
different now
and it's a good thing for the middle
east it's been under under strife for so
long and things may change
so that's what the situation is the
malaysians could likely acquire the lcds
maybe 20 or so and the if the egyptians
uh
take the deal
then they they could set up their own
first production facility over there
so it's it's a these are very good
developments when it comes to indian
defense manufacturing because we are now
in a position to actually
sell
these
uh
weapon systems and aircraft etc to other
countries and many countries are also
expressing an interest in acquiring
missiles from india like the brahmos for
instance so great developments very
positive developments
okay rio says
please shed some light on queen mary the
first before she ascended to the throne
of england the national religion of
england was protestantism
but as soon as she became the queen she
reinstalled catholicism as the national
religion to set an example to our people
who were questioning her decision and to
make them behave she burned hundreds of
protestant heretics
at the stake
western scholars are very hasty when it
comes to pointing out how apparently
regressive and discriminatory indian
caste system was etc but blatantly
turned a blind eye against their own
religion which is christianity
catholicism and protestant always being
in conflict and so on and going to wars
going on wars and crusades against one
another
uh this is an interesting chapter of
history so
who was queen mary the
first uh
so let's go back one generation the
father of queen mary the first was henry
viii
who ruled in the first half
of the 16th century from around 1510 to
about 1550 thereabouts
so henry viii was one of the one of the
most important kings of england his
father
was the essentially the founder of the
of the
of the tudor dynasty
he defeated uh robert
the third i believe in the battle of uh
i forget what the name of the battle is
look it up right that's not important so
henry viii was a guy who had many wives
and uh
he is an important very important figure
in english history he had three very
famous officials thomas wosley the
bishop who was the high chancellor of
england thomas moore who was also the
high chancellor of england and thomas
cromwell who was the chief minister and
uh
thomas moore and thomas cromwell were
beheaded on the orders of the king
and thomas woolsey was also under
uh he was also accused of treason but
before he could be beheaded he died of
natural causes and
henry
married multiple wives
his first wife was catherine of aragon
who was from spain
then he wanted he fell in love with a
lady called anne boleyn and he wanted to
marry her but he needed a divorce
from his first wife so he asked his
chancellor
uh thomas wosley to go to the vatican
and
meet the pope and acquire approval for a
divorce which thomas mosley was unable
to do and that's why he was accused of
reason
eventually
uh what happened is that henry viii
fell out with the vatican
and
he broke ties with the vatican and made
protestantism
the uh
official um state religion of england
and he broke with the vatican and the
anglican church was formed as a result
of this
which is still the the official i mean
the official church or whatever it is of
england
uh
so he then married anne boleyn
with
with his first wife catherine of aragon
he had a child who was married the first
marry
with anne boleyn he had
another child which was elizabeth
then he married a couple of other ladies
so anne boleyn was beheaded for whatever
reason
and another wife was also beheaded then
he also married a lady called jane
seymour
who
who had a son called edward and so on
so after henry viii died first of all
this guy called edward his son he came
to power he ruled for about five or six
years before he died
so after edward died
mary the daughter of catherine of aragon
became the queen of england she ruled
for about five or so years catherine of
aragon was a catholic
henry was
had adopted protestantism or whatever
you call it as the official religion so
when mary mary came to power
she i think she was upset with her
father because he had ill-treated
her mom catherine of aragon so mary
reversed her father's policies she
reinstated the catholic religion as the
official religion of england and then
she went on a rampage
and like you said she she burned lots of
people at the stake and
that was a brutal period in in english
history
so
mary ruled for about five or so years
she did not have any children and
eventually she died of ill health
she was called bloody mary that's how
bad she was
right and after she died her half-sister
elizabeth the daughter of anne boleyn
became the queen of england in
1558 1560 there abouts she ruled for
about 45 or 50 years
and that was the elizabethan age or the
golden age of england
and elizabeth again brought back the
protestant religion and
her rule was very enlightened
england became very stable and it
started
progressing science was allowed to
prosper
and there was a lot of scientific
development at the time
at the end of her rule of elizabeth
rule the east india company was formed
in 1600
and in 1608 it reached india in surat
and so on
so that is the story in brief so so this
lady jay uh what's her name
queen mary she was a terrible ruler she
did all kinds of atrocities on the
protestants and that is something that
is completely overlooked by western
historians
their uh their history is bloody it is
brutal
uh the the middle ages of of europe were
horrible
hundreds of thousands of women were
burned at the stake burned alive as
witches just to keep women under control
and
and so on yeah so it's it's a horrible
horrific history and it's completely
whitewashed out of out of
the history textbooks
and it's always the east that is
there is a portrait is regressive and
barbaric and primitive which when
actually the reverses
is true so yeah that is the hypocrisy of
the west and that's what we need to
push back against
lakshya says what factors led to the
fall of the roman empire and how is the
study of what caused the decline of
empires civilizations relevant even
today
all civilizations
rise and fall it's a cycle it's a cyclic
event they come they rise in the fall
civilizations
and empires are different
so the roman empire wasn't was not a
civilization it was an empire
so it rose because of great men
uh men like skipjoe africanus
men like pompey the great men like
julius caesar
augustus mark anthony
marcus aurelius great men great emperors
great conquerors
that's that's how the empire rose from
nothingness
uh
so it was an empire that was built upon
conquest
and it was vigorous and active and alive
as long as it was conquering
conquering in various directions in
europe in north africa and in the
mediterranean in the eastern
mediterranean region present-day lebanon
and israel and judea all that right
parts of the arabian regions as well
syria jordan and so on and so forth
anatolia all of that
so it was an empire built on conquest
now as the empire became larger and
larger
the mode shifted from conquest to
administration and bureaucracy now when
an empire goes into bureaucratic mode it
becomes
well it becomes less vigorous it becomes
more politicized so and and as it
expands
there is uh it becomes more difficult to
coordinate everything especially in an
age 2000 years before today roughly when
you do not have the communications
technology that we have today so you
could not instantaneously coordinate
what was happening you may have a battle
or a rebellion happening in judea
and the the emperor who is sitting in
rome will not come to know about what
happened for weeks on end
and then how do you relay your relay
orders to to the commander over there
these are all big problems that they
used to face so in
what happened is that you had these
various governors of various provinces
who would essentially rule autonomously
they were like kings in their own riot
they had their own legions of soldiers
and that would cause problems as well
and
after some time after some centuries you
had lots of emperors that came and went
very very
uh weak emperors
so that was that's what happens even
initially an empire rises because of
great men
great vigorous conquerors
then there is this phase of bureaucracy
and politics and that's what eventually
leads to the downfall as the empire
becomes more prosperous
and the wealth increases
people become more uh
people
lose their appetite
for hardship
you know what they say right hard times
give rise to strong men strong men give
rise to
good times good rise give good times
give rise to weak men soft men and which
again build brings on hard times and all
that so that's a cycle
so that's how the roman empire fell
that's how all empires rise and fall
that's the same thing happened to the
ottoman empire the same thing happened
to the mongol empire
and so on various indian empires as well
the mauryan empire the gupta empire
the
the uh kushan empire the chola empire
and so on it's a cyclical process
so that's what happened to rome
and if you understand these cycles of
history these patterns of history then
you can actually predict what's going to
happen
so you had the soviet empire you call it
a superpower it was an empire it was
about uh it controlled a significant
portion of the world
that also rose rapidly and fell
that's what happened and
right now we have
the anglo-saxon empire which which began
began with the east india company
and it's still in force in the form of
the u.s
well
uh the u.s hegemony in many parts of the
world so that may also decline someday
everything rises and falls
as part of a large cyclical process
so
okay rtk says can india become a
superpower without gaining back its
cultural identity let me give you a
historical example
you had something called the byzantine
empire a superpower is an empire please
understand that it's the same thing
in the 21st century anyone in the 20th
century we don't use the word empire
that's a bad word so use a different
word use the word superpower it's the
same thing a superpower is an empire
so we had something called the byzantine
empire which was the eastern roman
empire its capital city was
constantinople or byzantium
where is it do you know where it is i
hope you do otherwise i'll show you let
me show you where constantinople was
where is google maps
we were looking at india let's go east
uh let's go westwards
so byzantium
or constantinople which is now known
istanbul is over here
it's at the crossroads between
asia
and europe
right the strait of boss for us
so this is byzantium it's now known as
istanbul
so this was the capital of the eastern
roman empire or the byzantine empire
and this empire was in force for more
than a thousand years
then what happened
then the turks started encroaching on
on byzantine territory
and by 1453 or whatever the date is look
it up right i don't remember all the
dates
uh so eventually sultan muhammad ii
conquered
constantinople right
and they called it constantini in
turkish
and that was the birth of the ottoman
empire and then you had other sultans
who were greater than muhammad and it
all culminated with
with suleiman the magnificent
so they built the ottoman empire out of
the byzantine empire
and they called themselves kaiser arum
which means this is the caesar of rome
so they
they
considered themselves to be
uh
emperors who continued the byzantine
empire
at least that was the claim
that their empire was a continuation of
the byzantine empire
so what happened here is that
the ottoman empire or this region
anatolia
became a superpower
without
with a completely new cultural identity
a turkish islamic identity it was
a eastern roman
christian empire
which
transformed which was transformed into
a turkic turkish
islamic caliphate
that's what happened to the byzantine
empire it it
transmogrified into the ottoman empire
so the answer is yes a country can
become a superpower
in a completely new
cultural identity
and therefore the answer to this
question is india can become a
superpower without ever gaining back its
cultural identity
in the future you may have a completely
different kind of india
which is a superpower
maybe by 2100 we may have a different
kind of india with a totally different
cultural identity
and it may be a superpower it is a
possibility
yes
okay unwise sharma says what's your
opinion on the kali kilo ampere linear
injector weapon system developed by by
us
in 2016 our then our then defense
minister mr manohar parrikar refused to
answer grievances about kali
can it mean that this system has been
deployed
in various places or is it still under
development
is it only land-based or is it in planes
or in space or in aircraft and ships
etcetera joy makali joy makali
there is absolutely no information
available in the public domain about
this whatever this is the name is kilo
ampere linear injector that that kind of
reminds me of
something like a linear collider or
something right
and if it is kilo ampere that's a very
small voltage
uh
if
if you consider
machines like toka max
you have
giga ampere uh
energy in there so kilo ampere is like
is way underpowered of course this is
something that the the project may have
begun 20 30 years ago so at that time
kilo mps must have been a very high
amount of power for that time
so i don't know what the situation is
what the status is if it still exists if
it doesn't exist i have no idea because
there is absolutely no information
available in the public domain the
government has made no statements it has
released no information
so maybe this is a very highly
classified project
or maybe it's it's just something that
was used for experimental purposes and
maybe it doesn't exist anymore the name
is very nice kali so that kind of grabs
public imagination
and it has very interesting connotations
yeah because of the goddess but yeah we
don't know
i personally don't have any information
about what the status is if it is still
operational if it has gone to a new
level if it is an actual weapon
or whatever we don't know what it is
it could be that it's it's some kind of
weapon maybe a laser kind of thing or
whatever
but we don't have information in the
public domain and therefore that's why i
am not able to give you any specific
answer no idea whatsoever but if it is
being developed that's a good thing
i hope it is
but we don't have any uh information
bro bro says what is the strategy of
euro
asianism
eurasianism okay
what are your views on alexander dugan's
multipolarity where he proposes north
south coordination north america south
america europe africa russia india japan
southeast asia under against unipolar
american
structure do you think this is just
another feel-good idea like communism or
india
could present much more practicality in
the system
eurasianism
is the idea of a russian
okay
so
according to this idea of eurasianism
it's about russia
it says
its core principle or tenet is that
russia is not
a western
uh country
it's about um it's about russia becoming
an empire so russia is neither east nor
west that's what eurasianism says
that is the core principle or tenet of
eurasianism that russia is neither a
western entity or an eastern entity it's
somewhere in between it is definitely
not western it's eurasian
and it also says that russia should uh
become a eurasian empire
which is
located obviously in northern eurasia
the northern half of eurasia
and it would also say that russia would
need access to
warm
water ports maybe in the mediterranean
maybe in the indian ocean region or
wherever it can maybe that would
that would uh
uh for that they would need to conquer
perhaps iran or something like that you
know that's the kind of thing it is now
when it comes to alexander dugan's
multi-polarity
uh north south cooperation north america
america makes no sense because north
america is the us
and south america is totally under u.s
hegemony makes no sense there europe
africa has a master slave relationship
europe is the colonizer africa is still
colonized so it again makes no sense of
them cooperating when they have this
very very uh
colonial relationship
russia india makes a lot of sense japan
southeast asia japan and southeast asia
don't have very good history and japan
is right now a u.s lasalle state so it
makes no sense so the only cooperation
that makes sense in all of these
examples you've given is russia india
because india and russia have no
shared border they have no adversarial
adversarial relationship they have no
grounds for having any enmity
and there are lots and lots of areas in
which russia and india can cooperate and
work together
so russia and india are actually natural
allies
so yeah
when it comes to russia india
cooperation it makes sense it makes
sense and multi-polarity also makes
sense
so uh so in this world view russia would
not be a global hegemon but it would be
a major empire
uh
in in eurasia
stretching apparently from dublin to
vladivostok dublin ireland to
vladivostok in the far east of russia
and there would be cooperation with
major powers possibly like india
possibly like china china obviously is a
long term threat to russia
so
that cooperation would be issue based
and conditional and
time
uh
not long term cooperation so that's how
it is
so that is the great russian dream one
could say and alexander dugan is is a
geo strategist he's a philosopher of
some kind apparently they call him a
philosopher
and he's a russian nationalist
he
is a traditionalist a conservative
and he he
is somebody who believes in the
recreation of of a russian of a great
russian empire
so that's that's the that's the deal
with alexander dugan
do you think this is just another
feel-good idea communism it's not an
ideology like communism it's it's a
stated end goal for russia
so yeah it could be something that the
russians may be working towards
let's is it practical right now it is it
is still in the realm of dreams and
fantasy
but who knows
everything starts with dreams and
fantasies
it can be achieved practically things
like that can happen
especially with technology in the 21st
century so it is
a distant
possibility a distant dream but it is
not impractical it's not a feel-good
idea it is something the russians
possibly mr putin also would want to
achieve
so that's what
eurasianism is
i've noticed that in most parts of the
world nowadays the youth idolize and
look look up to hollywood
actors actresses entertainers comedians
cricket players and so on instead of
real heroes like people that have
actually had a genuine impact on
humanity like scientists historical
figures and freedom fighters but who do
who we choose to emulate has a huge
impact on our morals and behavior
how do you think this is influencing us
and is it cause for some of the bad
things that are happening in society
definitely
who you uh
the kind of people you hold as role
models is going to shape the kind of
society you have
a society that idolizes entertainers
is going to be as very very
it's not going to be a good society
and this is something that's a
phenomenon that has come out of the uh
um
post-world war ii
period of world history
so a period of u.s hegemony
and uh hollywood become very big
propaganda machine for the us
and even in u.s society people look up
to entertainers as role models
entertainers are simply people who are
paid to
pretend to be something that they are
not
and it's so easy for people to be fooled
by them
so for instance in india there are
certain bollywood actors
who portray
who play various roles
there is this one bollywood actor whom i
will not name
he had a number of movies in which he
which were like patriotic movies you
know in which it was about
about uh showing india in a good light
and patriotism and all that so people
started believing this guy is a great
patriot
i mean how silly is that and then he
came up with some movies that were
totally like the opposite of that
so that
woke people up but again
they will be fooled again in a few in a
few
when a few new movies come out
so people who uh a society that idolizes
entertainers is a society that is doomed
the romans had a very clear rule keep
entertainers far away from society
and taxed him heavily and the same was
the rule of uh that uh
vishnu gupta chanakya
spoke about i believe in his book the
arthashastra
that entertainers need to be heavily
taxed and they should not be allowed to
mingle too deeply with society they
should be on the margins of society i am
not saying these are bad people
and not against entertainers i'm not
against actors and actresses
they are also people many of them could
be good
but a society that idolizes
entertainers is a society that is doomed
so that's where we are today
that's the effect of the anglo-saxon
empire on the world
that we have the wrong role
models and the people who deserve to be
role models never get any visibility
so that is a big problem in the past it
was not the case
in the past you had a proper society in
india and other places as well
so yeah that's that's one of the major
problems of the 21st century
the wrong kind of influence
anybody can become an influencer
nowadays on on on um
what are the platforms instagram
tick tock is thankfully no longer
available in india but anyone can become
insta famous you go and do some dance or
something on instagram and you become
famous and people start following you
and everybody wants to be like you this
is
not a good thing for us for society
it it teaches the wrong lessons and the
wrong values so lecture is right
even cricketers i mean
it's it's it's not a bad thing to
succeed as a sports person but once
again uh
the thing is when you admire a person's
success you try to admire everything
else about the person now a cricketer is
a young
man or woman
who has
achieved a certain amount of success in
sport it doesn't mean that they're right
about everything in the world
there are so many of these idiotic
cricketers voc cricketers
former captains and all
who who
espouse the wrong ideas and
yeah so it's a problem so yeah this is
indeed the problem and i don't know what
the solution is right now but that's
something that we are going through
right now the entire world is going
through this
because of the power of social media the
power of propaganda and the power of the
entertainment industry
okay rama lakshmi says can you please
say something about india's mango
diplomacy which is which was used before
i saw in an article
are there more types to it like what
china uses will foreign diplomacy
so when they speak about mango diplomacy
it's about india giving mangoes as gifts
to various world leaders
that is not diplomacy
so in the past india i
used to send
crates of mangoes
to various world leaders to ambassadors
to presidents prime ministers etc to
please them
uh
that is not a diplomatic strategy but
that's what india india used to do so
that's all i can say about it that's all
it is it is not some great strategy or
anything it's about giving gifts
and trying to please people
that's not how you play diplomacy that's
not that's not how the game is played
the game
diplomacy is a substitute for warfare
that's what it is you negotiate
you bully
you nego you you try and extract
concessions
you do everything short of going to war
that is diplomacy and of course you you
enter into alliances you negotiate the
terms of the alliance
and all that that all is diplomacy you
you put your views forth
you make your position known to the
world
you know
you engage with the media all that is
diplomacy giving mangoes as gifts is not
diplomacy but that's what india's
foreign affairs establishment used to do
and thankfully all that nonsense is over
the world foreign diplomacy well that's
just aggressive behavior that's what it
is so the chinese foreign
uh
foreign affairs establishment were used
to be very conciliatory very meek they
used to swallow all the insults the
americans used to throw at them for the
longest time
uh their their leader then shopping had
a very famous maxim
which says that uh
bide your time hide your capabilities
and work very hard
and when the time comes you can do what
you want so the chinese followed that
maxim for longer for the longest time
it's only in 2012 onwards that their
entire post just posture
changed and they became very aggressive
and that's when the diplomats changed
their tune and they became uh
hyper aggressive in their in their
pronouncements in the statements
in their style of engaging with other
countries so that's what is called wolf
fourier diplomacy
so that's that is meant that is supposed
to reflect the newfound confidence of
the chinese nation which may sometimes
backfire or whatever but that's the
policy and the strategy that they are
using well let's see how that goes so
this mango diplomacy was a waste of time
complete waste of time it
i mean what was the point
so that's what it was
okay
couple more questions hopefully
pratik says i just completed the 12th i
naturally was inclined towards consumer
behavior
i knew how people like you business
people politicians influence choices and
i wanted to do business psychology
course but there isn't a single college
for in india for it why is business
psychology's importance still not
still very much unconquered in india
psychology is very important whether
it's business psychology or whatever
whether you are in sales or marketing or
entrepreneurship or negotiation or
business
whether you're a politician a world
leader diplomat whatever it is you need
to understand psychology even
if you just want to have a regular 9-5
job and career and rise up the corporate
ladder etc you need to understand
psychology it's very important and the
indian education system is obsolete it
is it is like still mired in the 1970s
so obviously there will be no courses
about business psychology in india
the good thing is you understand this
very few people understand that
so
learn it on your own you don't need a
degree to learn something
all the information you need is
available online
for free if you know where to look there
could be entire youtube courses you know
um
many of these of foreign universities
uni us universities etc have open
courseware in which they put up entire
semesters worth of lectures on youtube
for free
proper coursework academic coursework
you could go through that i'm sure there
are business psychology courses in that
and there could be other youtube
playlists or whatever on various
channels which could deal with this in a
different way there could be entire pdfs
and texts available on various websites
so look it up all the information is
available go and grab it
learn this and apply it in your life and
it's not just for pratik but for
everybody who's watching it psychology
is the knowledge of psychology human
psychology is is very important if you
want to succeed in life
uh for instance politicians
they have an intuiting
intuitive understanding of human
psychology mass psychology
it's essential for the survival and for
the success
if you're an army commander you need to
understand psychology
human psychology mass psychology what
motivates people what drives people
what what are the things that that
acts as as a deterrent for certain kind
of behavior and so on and so forth
right so psychology is very important
and
if you want to go into business and you
want to understand consumer behavior as
a marketer or a salesperson
or as a
product designer
strategist whatever you need to
understand human psychology business
psychology mass psychology and all that
so it's a very interesting field
you understand it well you have a
significant advantage of over your peers
so i would recommend that
go ahead learn it on your own it doesn't
matter that there are no courses
available in indian colleges who cares
learn it for free
yeah go ahead all the best
okay this is a longer thing if the khara
khan says india was the richest and
therefore strongest before the judo
christians arrived
we all know the rich west dominates the
world anyway it wants it was in fact the
judeo-christian west that through
centuries of crusades slavery
invasions and colonization that they
massacred and plundered et cetera others
to accumulate trillions and build their
empire that oppresses all others from
growing subsequently through this
plundering they destroyed many including
india economists clearly know that they
looted 45 trillion usd from india after
massacring at least 100 million indians
and breaking it into three thus
weakening india like no other in the
process they enslaved indian minds for
which some believe that the english
language is a blessing well i'm glad you
understand this
more and more people are now beginning
to understand this and beginning to
realize what really has happened
the english language is not a boon or a
blessing to india it is a curse that
needs to be removed
they today portray themselves as the as
the
defenders of human rights
and democracy when they are the ones
that have undermined human rights and
democracy the most
in the world they speak about equality
they are the worst
oppressors the worst opponents of
equality when it comes to i mean we know
what the truth is
so
we need to educate ourselves about this
we need to understand what really
happened the true history of the world
what the west has really done
they
are the ones that have destroyed the
rest of the world
the americas
africa
and asia
the east needs to rise again
whether together or separately is is it
remains to be seen
and like-minded
nations
should come together and work together
and we will rise again
and i would like india to rise again
very much
i think it's india's destiny to rise
again to its rightful place in the world
and i don't think anybody will be able
to stop this
so
yeah so i'm glad people are realizing
this and
whatever you said is absolutely right
okay
let's take a couple of maybe uh live
chat questions if anybody has
live chat questions if you have any
questions let me know right now put them
in the chat and i will take a look at
that
and hopefully
take a few of those
uh
what do we have
what are your thoughts about the ghatak
ucav project did i
not just speak about that
i answered that
the drdo ghatak project
it is something that is currently being
developed we have
tested a scaled down version of it
it has worked well and now we will take
it forward it's a good thing
all right what next what else do we have
um
if pakistan splits which parts will be
favorable to india if it splits all
parts will be favorable to india and
favorably incline to india provided we
play our cards right
um
will india ever be equal to china in
terms of gdp india will eventually
exceed the gdp of china
over time it won't happen tomorrow next
week next year
in the next by 2050 it could happen it
is a possibility
by 2100 definitely india will be number
one
but yeah i know that's that's too far
away and we want it now but
it's all about patience listen we we
have to
we have to realize we are a civilization
and we are a small we are small links in
the long chain
we have to think in terms of centuries
and we have to all play our part india
will be
number one again but it will take time
it will take time
okay some other con some other questions
did pashtuns really want to join india
khanna bulgar khan when he returned told
congress that they had left them to the
wolves well
yes khan abdul ghaffar khan wanted a
unified india
he was a pashtun
when he died he was buried i believe in
jalalabad in afghanistan
and he wanted a unified india
so he was a pashtun his in his politic
his political movement was called the
madgars
uh they were all pashtuns
a completely non-violent movement
yeah
he fought
for a unified india
mr gandhi agreed to the partition of
india to no one's great surprise
and when this happened khanna big
in his last meeting with gandhi i
believe
told him that you have thrown us to the
wolves
and after the partition of india khan
abdul kafar khan spent the
majority of the rest of his life under
house arrest in pakistan
so that's the tragic story of this great
man he was a true patriot a true indian
more patriotic and more indian than
certain other leaders you can think of
so yeah
it doesn't mean that the pashtuns of
afghanistan wanted to join india but the
pashtuns who lived in pakistan under his
leadership wanted a unified india that's
what they were fighting for
and they were betrayed
okay
certain questions are being repeated but
let's see
what else do we have
there are mentions of ufos in indian
literature in rigveda
how come we are still so clueless about
it um
uh so that's interesting i have never
heard of this
uh if you have come across this you
could put that in the comments where
exactly in which part of the rig veda
there is a mention of ufos and i'll
certainly look into that as far as i
know i've never heard of this before but
if it is true that would be really
interesting
so please do that please put that in the
comments not in the chat
when this live stream is over put that
in the comments if you have the actual
references and i will certainly take a
look at that
um
what books do you
like in fiction genre i want to start
reading just like you
um
in fiction i used to read a lot of
science fiction a lot of science fiction
all the greats in science fiction asimov
arthur c clarke
and so on
nowadays i have other books
in other
newer
writers you may not have seen my other
book collection i have way more books
here we will see that later
so on so yeah
i
i like detective fiction i like
historical fiction i like science
fiction uh
what books do i like
i'll i read as many books as i can i
don't have any
i don't have any list of books that i
can tell you i don't even remember how
many books i've read so i would say
read as much as you can
and if you want to know what which books
are good go to amazon see the reviews
books that have
good ratings 4.4 4.5 and above with lots
of reviews that those are typically good
books hopefully
the wisdom of the masses is not always
good wisdom but that typically is an
indicator that a book would be
reasonably good so you could start like
that
okay
i i think we are the end of today's
session two hours plus already
so yeah let's end it here
thank you very much for all of your
questions as always interesting
fascinating questions some of them
and let's continue this next week thank
you very much
take care stay healthy stay safe
walk out every day
and keep going take take care thank you
bye